Finding Aid for Andrew S. Watson Papers, 1952-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Andrew S. Watson papers 1952-1998
Watson, Andrew S. (1920-1998)
4 motion picture films
4.25 linear feet
02115 Aa 2
University of Michigan law school professor combining training in law and psychiatry.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Joyce L. Watson (Donor No. 9214 ) in June 2002.
The collection is open except for case files in restricted box 5.
Andrew S. Watson, M.D., was a pioneer in bringing together the fields of psychiatry and law, helping to establish an interdisciplinary approach in the discipline. Watson brought his training as a psychiatrist to bear in legal cases, using psychiatry to explain both criminal behavior and the legal negotiation process. He was also interested in the lawyer-client relationship and was a critic of traditional law school training, challenging the profession to think differently about educational methods.
Watson's published work includes Psychiatry for Lawyers, The Lawyer in the Interviewing and Counseling Process, chapters in books, and numerous articles in scholarly journals.
Watson was born on May 2, 1920, in Highland Park, Michigan, and received his undergraduate degree in zoology from the University of Michigan in 1942, subsequently serving as captain in the U.S. Army Medical Administrative Corps from 1942-1946. Upon leaving the Army, Watson went on to obtain his medical degree from Temple University in 1950 and completed postgraduate training at the University of Pennsylvania Graduate Hospital and Temple University. He continued his psychoanalytic studies and graduated from the Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute in 1960.
While completing his graduate training, Watson served as a special instructor at the Bryn Mawr School of Social Work from 1954-1959, while also serving as Assistant Professor of Psychiatry and Associate Professor of Psychiatry and Law at the University of Pennsylvania. Watson came to the University of Michigan in 1959, and attained full professorship status in both law and psychiatry in 1966. Watson spent the remainder of his career at the university, retiring in 1990 with Emeritus status in both law and medicine.
In addition to his teaching appointment and private psychiatry practice, Watson served in a number of consulting capacities at the state and local levels. From 1959 to 1970, Watson served as consultant for the Michigan Department of Corrections, while also serving as consultant for the Veterans Administration Hospital in Ann Arbor from 1959 to 1960 and the Washtenaw County Juvenile Court and Department of Public Welfare from 1961 to 1966. Watson also served as a witness in a number of high profile criminal cases throughout the country, including Jack Ruby, Twiggs Lyndon and John Norman Collins.
In 1967, Watson was honored as the Robert S. Marx Lecturer by the University of Cincinnati's College of Law. He received the Isaac Ray Award from the American Psychiatry Association in 1978, and later received the Association's Seymour Pollack Distinguished Achievement Award in 1989.
Watson passed away on April 2, 1998, leaving behind his wife, Joyce, and four sons.
The Andrew S. Watson Papers document the professional career of a scholar, practicing psychiatrist, and teacher. The papers include correspondence, lecture notes and other course materials, published and unpublished writings, and several instructional films in which Watson appeared. The collection is arranged into four series: Biographical, Professional, Audiovisual, and Case Files.
Subjects:
Watson, Andrew S., 1920-1998.; Law--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Watson, Andrew S., 1920-1998.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series (0.1 linear ft., 1959-1978, 1990, 1995) includes Watson's curriculum vitae and bibliography, providing a complete picture of his work as a scholar. A limited amount of correspondence is contained in the collection, the majority of which are written to and received from politicians, about policy issues and appointments. Correspondents include Warren Burger, Michigan governors Romney and Milliken, and numerous state senators.
  - Bibliography circa 1990 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1959-1978, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae 1990 (Box 1)
  - Emeritus Status 1990 (Box 1)
  - News Clippings (Box 1)
  - Obituary 1998 (Box 1)
  - Photographs undated (Box 1)
- Professional
  The Professional series (1.9 linear feet, 1950-1993) is contains four subseries: Course Materials, Lectures, Writings, and Miscellaneous. The Course Materials subseries is the most extensive portion of the collection, including Watson's lecture notes and course manuals, exam materials, and some student evaluations of Watson. The majority of Watson's published work is included in the collection, as well as some drafts with the comment of collaborators and some unpublished materials. These materials provide the researcher with background information on Watson's scholarly pursuits. Most notable among the unpublished work are Watson's notes from a 13-month sabbatical in England from 1966 to 1967, where he studied and observed the British legal system.
  - Course Materials
    - Forensic Psychiatry Seminars 1977 (Box 1)
    - Inteflex 101 Seminar 1973 (Box 1)
    - Law and Psychiatry, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Lawyer as Negotiator, Fall 1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (includes notes from 1988 and 1991)
    - Legal Problems Associated with Child Psychotherapy 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Negotiation Techniques in Divorce 1991 (Box 1)
    - Negotiation Techniques in the Personal Injury Case 1982 (Box 1)
    - Neural and Behavioral Sciences 500
      - Exam Materials 1972-1973 (Box 1)
      - Lecture Notes 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Neural and Behavioral Sciences 600
      - Evaluations of Watson 1974 (Box 1)
      - Lecture Notes 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Lectures
    - "Home Run or Strike Out? -- The Happy Family," 1962 Mental Health Series, April 13, 1962 (Box 1)
    - "Honors Convocation Address," University of Michigan Law School May 10, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Isaac Ray Award Lectures February 13-15, 1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Marx Lecture Introduction November 17, 1967 (Box 1)
    - "The Child Learns to Love," Temple University Hospital circa 1952 (Box 1)
    - "The Psychiatrist as an Expert Witness," Psychopathic Hospital, Iowa City, IA November 7, 1964 (Box 1)
    - "Discussion: 'Psychiatry and Individual Liberties,'" circa 1965 (Box 1)
    - Untitled undated (Box 1)
  - Writing
    - Published
      - Reprints
        - 1950s (Box 1)
        - 1960s (Box 1)
        - 1970s (Box 2)
        - 1980s (Box 2)
        - 1990s (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, Comments, and Draft of "On Some Legal and Psychotherapeutic Implementation Tactics for 'Beyond the Best Interest of the Child,'" 1975 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence and Draft, "Discussion Leader's Manual for 'No Such Thing as A Juvenile Delinquent,'" 1975-1976 (Box 2)
      - Outside Reviews (Box 2)
    - Unpublished
      - Manual for a Teaching Method to Provide Experiential Learning on Legal Ethics and Professionalism circa 1975 (Box 2)
      - "Problems of 'Self-Image' in Coping with Child Abuse and Neglect," circa 1980 (Box 2)
      - Sabbatical Notes
        - Accounts of Training Programs 1966-1967 (Box 2)
        - Accounts of Various Law School Events 1966-1967 (Box 2)
        - Legal Process Observations 1966-1967 (Box 2)
        - Misc. Lectures and Seminar Notes 1966 (Box 2)
      - "Teaching and Learning about Some Psychological Factors in Mediation and Negotiation," circa 1970 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Advocacy Institute 1963 (Box 2)
    - Association of American Law Schools, Law Teaching Clinic Project 1975 (Box 2)
    - Child Abuse Project 1977 (Box 2)
    - Proposal for A Study of the Institutionalization of Mentally Abnormal Persons 1965 (Box 2)
- Audiovisual
  The Audiovisual series (2.0 linear feet, ca. 1969-1977) contains films in a number of formats and present Watson in a variety of settings. Of particular note is a series of films, "On Teaching Legal Ethics and Professionalism in the Clinical Setting," which were produced by Watson and other professors at the University of Michigan Law School (Pepe, Schulte and Kerr), with sponsorship and financial support from the Council on Legal Education for Professional Responsibility (CLEPR). This series of films was likely produced as an educational tool for use in other schools of law and in the training of young lawyers, and feature Watson and his colleagues as facilitators of legal seminars. In the film titled "The Lawyers Psyche," Watson presents a talk at a professional conference, and in the Mother-Father-Homosexual Son film (also referred to as the "St. Louis Interview") Watson engages a family in a discussion about their son's behavior.
  - Motion Pictures
    - Dr. Ackerman Interview/Program circa 1970, 4 reels; 35 mm (Box 3)
  - Videotapes, audiotapes 3/4-inch.; reel-to-reel tapes; 1-inch
    - Advocacy Institute
      - Direct and Cross of Dr. Burton 1977, reels 3/4-inch (Box 3)
      - Cross Examination of Dr. Watson May 14, 1977, reels 3/4-inch (Box 3)
    - Council on Legal Education for Professional Responsibility (CLEPR), Inc. unidentified circa 1976, reels 3/4-inch (Box 3)
    - Family Law April 22, 1974, reels 3/4-inch (Box 3)
    - Human Relations (Audience Reaction on the Dynamics of the Correction Officer and the Inmate) September 9, 1971, reels 3/4-inch (Box 3)
    - Mother-Father-Homosexual Son (also called "St. Louis Interview) 1974, 2 reels; 1-inch reels (Box 3)
  - Videotapes: U-matic
    - The Lawyers Psyche, Parts I and 2 circa 1970, 2 tapes (Box 4)
    - Mother-Father-Homosexual Son 1974 (Box 4)
      (also called "St. Louis Interview")
    - "On Teaching Legal Ethics and Professionalism in the Clinical Setting"
      - #1: Demonstration of a Clinical Conference. 1976 (Box 4)
      - #2: Lawyer Role Conflicts and Their Resolution: Learning Through Group Process 1976 (Box 4)
      - #3: Psychological Taxonomy of Lawyer Conflicts 1976 (Box 4)
      - #4: A Clinical Case Conference 1976 (Box 4)
      - #6: Clinical Conference on Counsel's Life v. Client's Needs 1976, 2 tapes (Box 4)
  - Audio
    - John Collins Interview September 8, 1969, 1 audiocassettes (Box 4)
    - L&P Classes circa 1970, 3 reels; Reel-to-Reel (Box 4)
- Case Files [RESTRICTED]
  [RESTRICTED]
  Included in the Case Files series are a limited number of high-profile cases in which Watson served as expert witness. These files include correspondence, notes from interviews with the accused, news clippings, strategy for testimony, and background information. These files are restricted until clearance has been received from the donor.
  - John Norman Collins 1969-1977 (Box 5)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2077 ]
  - Twiggs Lyndon
    - Background Information 1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2070 ]
    - Correspondence 1971-1972 (Box 5)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2072 ]
    - Exhibit Information 1971 (Box 5)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2071 ]
    - Interview with Lyndon 1971 (Box 5)
    - Interviews regarding Lyndon 1971 (Box 5)
    - Joint Report on Lyndon August 25, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Testimony Outline 1971 (Box 5)
  - Jack Ruby 1964-1966 (Box 5)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2066 ]